<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>UBC Chem-E-Car: The University of British Columbia</title>
    <link>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/categories/design/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on UBC Chem-E-Car: The University of British Columbia</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright (C) 2016 UBC Chem-E-Car. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://www.ubcchemecar.com/categories/design/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Biofuels Project</title>
      <link>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2017/01/19/biofuels/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2017/01/19/biofuels/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;prologue&#34;&gt;Prologue&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Casually during our regular weekday meeting, Siang and Thanos discussed the idea of having two teams from Chem E Car present posters at the annual Generate conference hosted by Clean Energy BC. We decided to be that second team. With less than a month away, we had to choose a topic, become experts in that topic and design a poster in hopes of winning the competition and $500 prize money. What started off as a one-time project has turned into a team interest and has some of our members looking to pursue it further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As one of the fastest growing plants, algae uses sunlight more effectively than any other plant resulting in it having up to 2x higher energy production compared to other crops. With a composition of 50% oil by dry weight, algae is the ideal crop to use for biofuel. After significant technological advancements in growing algae, oil extraction, and biofuel conversion, the overall cost can potentially be reduced to USD $1.94 per gallon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/biofuels/biofuels.png&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/biofuels/biofuels.pdf&#34;&gt;Our beautiful biofuels poster&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;growth-of-algae&#34;&gt;Growth of Algae&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When compared to other oil producing crops, algae can produce up to 10 times more oil per hectare of land. Algae can also grow in a wide variety of environments, including saltwater, freshwater, glaciers, and even wastewater. Since algae grows in water, algae can be grown on non arable land. Algae uses sunlight and CO2 to grow, which means that CO2 emissions from power plants and factories that are normally sequestered into the ground can be redirected to grow algae, and make the biofuel a carbon sink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;production-methods&#34;&gt;Production methods&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two main methods of growing algae, open systems and closed systems. Open systems have low control over the process, low productivity, low operation costs, and high contamination risk when compared to closed systems. This contrast causes a large argument over which method is superior. At the moment, open systems are more favourable since they are much cheaper. We believe that when the technology improves, closed systems will be the future of algae farming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;future-of-algae&#34;&gt;Future of Algae&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a lack of affordable technology, algae biofuels are currently a very expensive alternative to traditional fossil fuels. Despite this, from a research perspective, algae biofuels have the highest potential to replace these traditional fossil fuels. A lot of work needs to be done before algae becomes the leader of energy production for the transportation industry. The sheer magnitude of algae that can be produced from a small plot of non-arable land makes it the only viable option that can replace Big Oil and save our world from climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;poster&#34;&gt;Poster&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out our poster for more information: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/biofuels/biofuels.pdf&#34;&gt;Poster Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beer Homebrew Project</title>
      <link>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2017/01/12/beer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2017/01/12/beer/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the Student AIChE/CACHE National Mobile Device APP Competition around the corner, our team has been working hard in exploring different ideas to showcase our creativity in a practical design. As part of our lab course field trips, many of us have visited local breweries to gain a general overview of how the general brewing process works. Keeping this in mind, we decided to try something that none of us have done before: creating an app to automate the brewing of craft beer. To create this app, we first had to be confident in carrying out the brewing process itself. Thus, we are proud to present the CHBE Brewing team, a sub-division of the Chem-E-Car team!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/beer/logo.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Logo design courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amandapenuta.com/&#34;&gt;Amanda Penuta&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;literature-review&#34;&gt;Literature Review&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We began with browsing the web on what kind of equipment would be required to begin brewing. Without any prior experience in brewing, it was difficult to know whether we really &lt;strong&gt;needed&lt;/strong&gt; that $300 &amp;ldquo;All-in-One Reactor&amp;rdquo;. Instead, we chose to drop by some local homebrewing businesses to learn more about the process. We ended up going to Centennial Homebrewing Supplies and speaking with the owner, Brian Janzen. Brian was extremely informative, guiding us through the steps of homebrewing; from choosing the right equipment for beginner brewing, to bottling the brew at the very end. His tutorial can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mxdreV_tN1Y/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-brewing-process&#34;&gt;The Brewing Process&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/beer/flowchart.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Overview of the extract brewing process that we followed.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sanitizing&#34;&gt;Sanitizing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed with this new knowledge, we purchased the equipment and got to work. We began with sanitizing all the equipment with Sani-brew (1 tbsp. powder/L of water) cleaning solution. This is to ensure that chance of bacterial growth or contamination is minimized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mashing&#34;&gt;Mashing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step is to &amp;ldquo;mash the grains&amp;rdquo;. Contrary to what we initially thought, it had nothing to do with physically mashing the grains. This step involved adding 1L of water for each lb of grain that we had (2.5L of water in our case) to a pot and bringing the temperature up to ~145 to 155°F (~63 to 68°C). This mixture was then allowed to steep for about 60 minutes. Due to the uneven heating from the stove we were using, the grains ended up being slightly burnt&amp;hellip; but that just adds more flavor to the brew, right? (To be confirmed)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sparging&#34;&gt;Sparging&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the grains were steeping, another pot of water was heated up to about 175°F (~79°C). This pot of water was used in the sparging (rinsing) step. This was done by pouring the steeped grains mixture into a colander, and the additional water through the grains into another pot. The liquid that drains through is the base of our wort, while the spent grains were disposed of. The liquid malt extract was added to the wort base and stirred well until the mixture was uniform. This was done before the stove was turned on to prevent the mixture from burning and sticking to the bottom of the pot. The mixture was then brought to a boil. During this boiling time, the primary fermenter was sanitized using the Sani-brew cleaning solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;boiling&#34;&gt;Boiling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the wort was boiling, we set a timer for 60 minutes of boiling. Throughout this timeframe, hops were added at different times. For example, the Pacific ESB we were making required the 3 bags of hops to be added in at 0 minutes (beginning of boil), 45 minutes, and 55 minutes of boiling time. Once the boiling time was complete, the wort was then plunged into an ice bath to cool it down. As Vancouver has been experiencing heavy snowfall (by our standards), our ice bath consisted of snow and ice taken from right outside our doorstep. Once the wort reached a temperature of around ~69 to 73°F (~20.5 to 23°C), it was poured into the primary fermenter. The primary fermenter was topped off with water so the total volume of the brew was about 23L, with the temperature being around 21°C for optimal yeast pitching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;fermenting&#34;&gt;Fermenting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the yeast was added to the wort, a test was conducted using a hydrometer. This showed the starting gravity of the wort, with the potential final alcohol content (around 6.5% for our brew). The yeast was added to the wort and the primary fermenter was sealed with an airlock (this allows carbon dioxide to escape during fermentation, but nothing to go into the brew). The primary fermenter was then left to sit for about a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conditioning&#34;&gt;Conditioning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a week of fermentation, the brew was transported into the carboy for conditioning and additional fermentation. The brew was siphoned out using a tube with a filter attached to the end to prevent larger solids from going through. Once all the brew was transported to the carboy, it was sealed with another airlock and left to sit for another week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a total of two weeks of fermentation, the brew was about ready to bottle. Another test was done with the hydrometer (pictured below) to see if the fermentation was near completion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/beer/hydrometer.jpg&#34; height=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;It was recommended that the reading on the hydrometer to be around 1008 to 1010, which indicates that fermentation was near completion. Our reading was roughly 1014, so pretty close.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bottling-and-carbonation&#34;&gt;Bottling and Carbonation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, the brew was basically flat (not a lot of carbonation). The next step involved adding &lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; cup of dextrose (priming sugar) into the brew before bottling. Since the bottles are left capped for two more weeks, the priming sugar causes carbonation to occur. The brew was siphoned into two types of bottles that we purchased: 1L EZ-cap bottles and 330mL bottles with crown caps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/beer/capper.jpg&#34; height=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Capping is hard work. (No, it&amp;rsquo;s not)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/beer/bottles.jpg&#34; height=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Bottled and ready to drink! (In two weeks)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we just need to wait about one more week from this time of posting for the carbonation to finalize. Hopefully we will have great tasting beer to drink!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solder Fan System</title>
      <link>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2017/01/01/solder-fan-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2017/01/01/solder-fan-system/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing around with old computer power supplies. Naturally, that led me to other components of the computer, namely, the cooling fan. These fans are driven by a brushless DC motor system. This is to achieve a reduced sound and higher efficiency compared to a brushed DC motor system such as those you would see (or hear) in printers, air conditioners and RC cars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computer fans can range from very simple to kind-of-simple with 2, 3, and 4 wires coming out of it. The 2 wire configuration is the simplest and this is just power and ground. A third wire is introduced to be able to monitor the speed of the fan. This is done most commonly by using a hall sensor to measure the rotations of the rotors around the commutator. The 4th wire adds PWM control to the fan so that consumers can control the speed of the fan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/solder-fan/2wirefan.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;A two wire fan circuit. Check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://pcbheaven.com/wikipages/How_PC_Fans_Work/&#34;&gt;PCB Heaven&lt;/a&gt; for more info&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How useful are these fans? Under normal operating temperatures, the pi typically reaches ~68 C, and ~80 C when performing calculations or running a video. With the fan, the temperature is quickly lowered to ~37 C. Another use for these fans is for soldering. They create a vaccuum to garner the toxic fumes from the solder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soldering fumes are bad for you! They are a mix of lead, and rosin evaporated into a gas. Always have good ventilation when you solder. I use my PC fans to create a solder fume extractor that I would otherwise, have to buy commercially &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.digikey.ca/product-detail/en/apex-tool-group/WSA350/WSA350-ND/1130559&#34;&gt;like this&lt;/a&gt;. I created a tiny switch board for my fans and I had them running! This was a good start but it didnt fully solve the problem as the fumes were merely being diluted. To rectify this I bought some carbon filters and attached them onto my fans. The trade-off is that this lowers the volume of air displaced by the fan but fumes actually become trapped by the carbon filter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The circuit I used was a simple switch inline to a computer power supply to power the fans. I am a large fan (no pun intended) of modularity, the ability to switch and recombine components. Sometimes, I need the power supply for a different task, or I need the fan to be cooling rather than extracting particulates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My circuit was simple enough that I didnt need a breadboard. I also wanted my circuit to be more permanent and didn&amp;rsquo;t want to spend time or money making a PCB, so I went with a perf board. Perfboards come in many varieties with copper strips exactly like a breadboard or long strips down the board but they are known traditionally as boards with arrays of little holes punched into them and copper vias surrounding them to create a contact for soldering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perfboards are a step behind making an actual PCB that you would see inside any electronic component but I believe that they are more difficult to make. With CAD software out there such as EAGLECAD or Fritzing, making a PCB is very visual. The graphical interfaces allow you to easily create a route and undo it with a simple click of a button. With a perfboard it is more difficult as there isn&amp;rsquo;t this interface. Planning it becomes a lot more tedious with pencil and paper and having to make iterations&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/solder-fan/circuit.jpg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my perfboard I used two rows of header pins to allow multiple fan systems as well as the connection to the power supply. A set-screw hub enable the switch to be inserted and removed at a moments notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I just need to wait for my fans to come in from the internet (that was a pun)!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Importance of Trial and Error</title>
      <link>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2016/11/24/trial-and-error/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2016/11/24/trial-and-error/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome everyone to the first of (hopefully) many blog posts for the UBC Chem-E-Car Team. The purpose of these posts is to give you, the reader insight into how our organization is run. Through this we hope to generate interest in our organization and to help get other students involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The topic of our first post is on the importance of trial and error. Most people will look at a finished product and comment on how sleek or amazing it is; while conveniently ignoring that it took years of tinkering and modifications for that item to even function properly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First let’s take a look at the first electronic circuit that I ever made for Chem-E-Car:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/trial-and-error/first.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;First&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entire device is a mess! There are wires everywhere, tons of unused board real estate, and parts that have to be tied together to fit on the board. Likewise, unsecured parts have a very unreliable connection and break off easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the summer I made a new model with the focus of eliminating loose wires and better utilizing space, this is the result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/trial-and-error/second.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Second&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This model utilizes a lot less space, is easy to stack, and most of the components are stabilized on the board itself. However, during assembly I needed a lot of extra parts since directly soldering them often destroyed the part if not done properly. Another issue is that the model needed 4 stacks (making it really tall), and the lights and switches were not necessary. Now let’s look at the second iteration:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/trial-and-error/third.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Third&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The board is even MORE compact, features detachable modules for easy replacement, and utilizes an SD card and opto-gate for recording data. However, the connectors were unreliable, the copper on the board was unprotected and prone to damage which destroyed the circuit at times, and data could not be read in real time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To fix these issues I developed a 4th and final board:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/trial-and-error/fourth.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Fourth&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This system uses reliable connectors that can only be inserted in one direction, is completely modular (easy to replace destroyed parts), has a silkscreen layer that protects the circuit, only uses one layer, and utilizes a bluetooth system for real time data collection on a mobile phone!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an image of all the circuits for an overall comparison:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/trial-and-error/comparison.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Comparison&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;reflections&#34;&gt;Reflections&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These circuits are 1.5 years of continuous design and iteration, with each model having its flaws analyzed and corrected. They were made by an entry level chemical engineering student with NO prior experience or knowledge of electronics. The moral of the story? Good design is all about making something, figuring out what works and doesn’t work then rebuilding it until it sort of works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/trial-and-error/quote.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Quote&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to any beginner in terms of design, don’t despair! Rather look at what you can learn from your prototype and how it can be improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that sense it is important to seek the feedback of experienced individuals. Their experience (in how NOT to do things wrong by doing it wrong) is invaluable for any would-be inventor. Look at how others have done things and learn accordingly from it. Finally remember, every master in a subject started from knowing nothing; the difference between them and the amateurs is that they never stopped trying to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>