<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog-rsses on UBC Chem-E-Car: The University of British Columbia</title>
    <link>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog-rsses on UBC Chem-E-Car: The University of British Columbia</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright (C) 2017 UBC Chem-E-Car. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Chem-E-Car Electrical System</title>
      <link>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2017/02/11/elecsystem/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2017/02/11/elecsystem/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the “Chem-E-Car Reaction Mechanism” article, Jayg and Josh talk about the iodine clock reaction and how a light-dependent resistor (LDR) is part of the stopping mechanism. The LDR changes electrical resistance depending on how much light is hitting it; as light intensity increases, resistance drops, and vice versa. Theoretically, if we shone light on an LDR in an iodine solution as its colour went dark, light intensity as measured at the LDR’s surface would fall. This is the basis of our stopping mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;system-overview&#34;&gt;System Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our system consists of two main circuits, a MOSFET (N-channel transistor) circuit and an LDR circuit. The transistor circuit is used to control LEDs that are held in place within the reaction vessel, and the LDR circuit controls LDRs used for the stopping mechanism. Both circuits are connected to our Arduino microcontroller, which is central to the electrical system. Below is a basic diagram for the system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/elecsystem/elec1.png&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; the Arduino board is also connected to the motor of the car via another MOSFET, which is not shown in the circuit diagram.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of software, our team mostly used Arduino to generate and test the codes for the car. I also used Eagle software to design the circuit diagram above, and to create an effective circuit that can be printed on a circuit board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mosfet-circuit&#34;&gt;MOSFET Circuit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MOSFET circuit connects our LEDs to the Arduino. The Arduino board works with a fairly small current, and so when the voltage across the LDRs changes during the stopping mechanism, the difference between voltage readings is small. We can amplify these signals by using a MOSFET, which is the whole idea behind having it in the circuit. With a big enough voltage difference, the risk of stopping at the wrong time is greatly reduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As shown in the diagram, the MOSFET has its gate pin connected to an Arduino digital pin (D9-1), its source pin connected to the wire coming from LED1 and LED2, and its drain pin connected to the 5V supply from the Arduino. Physically, the circuit will be on a printed circuit board made in the workshop used by Chem-E-Car, and will be separated from the LDRs as explained below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ldr-circuit&#34;&gt;LDR Circuit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our LDR circuit connects the Arduino to the 2 LDRs, and allows the Arduino to record the voltages across them using its built-in analog pins. Using the analog pins, we set threshold values of voltage which, when crossed, enable the Arduino to cut off power to the motor, which will stop the car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LDRs are placed across from the LEDs in the reaction vessel. This is to allow maximum light exposure from the LEDs, and so the LDRs need to be physically separated from the circuit board.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s Brewing* in The Lab?</title>
      <link>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2017/02/05/beer2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2017/02/05/beer2/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; What&amp;rsquo;s brewing, figuratively, not literally. The lab is not food safe, NO FOOD OR DRINKS IN THE LAB!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you may have read in part one, our team is working on an app to automate the brewing of craft beer. To understand the homebrewing process we made a batch of Pacific ESB, an ale that is light with a crisp bitter aftertaste. We made a few mistakes throughout the process (&lt;strong&gt;BURNT GRAINS&lt;/strong&gt;) but learned from those mistakes to make the second batch better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we need to do next is prepare our sensors and electronics. Primarily, the qualities we are looking for are &lt;strong&gt;alcohol content&lt;/strong&gt;, acidity, and temperature. We want to ensure that the data we collect is reliable and accurate for our app and future users so we took the time to work with them and learn them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sensors-and-devices&#34;&gt;Sensors and Devices&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First is the DS18b20 temperture sensor from Adafruit. This is a 1-wire temperature sensor that is simple and easy too setup. It requires no external components, can be powered by logic level (5V) and like each and everyone of us, it has unique 64 bit serial code stored into its ROM memory. What this means is that we can connect up to 63 device to 1 arduino port. With this configuration protocol we will be hooking up 4 of these sensors to the arduino to measure ambient temperature, the temperature of our cooling device, and the temperature of the brew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/beer2/tempsen.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Temperature sensor&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adafruit&amp;rsquo;s temperature sensor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we want to measure alcohol content, homebrewers measure the specific gravity of the batch. Since alcohol is less dense than water the specific gravity measurement will be lower after the fermentation process. Our goal will to measure the change in weight of a suspended mass inside the batch. To do so we want a device that measure force applied i.e weight. This is our load cell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/beer2/loadcell.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Load cell&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sparkfun load cell&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last device in this set is a Thermoelectric cooler, otherwise known as the Peltier plate. A temperature difference between two different metals will create a voltage difference and the converse is true as well. That means, by pumping electricity, we can reach teamperatures as low as -5C and 60C at once. For us this means a system that can heat and cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/beer2/peltier.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Peltier plate&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Peltier Plate&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;testing&#34;&gt;Testing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our goal was to make sure all of our equipment was working and seeing if anything needed calibration. Then we wanted to create a test situation where we would use the peltier plate to cool water while wew measured the temperature and weight of the water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first drawbacks is that the Load cell did not work. Data was not being sent and the values we had were ridiculous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/beer2/test1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Load Cell Wiring&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The temperature sensors went much better.  The design of the sensor was plug &amp;amp; play and we were getting data fast and accurately in minutes. Chaining them in series took some time. We had to get to know each and everyone of them and their adresses but it worked and worked without a hitch it did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/beer2/test2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two temperature sensors here measure ambient temperature and water temperature&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when you have a pelteir plate one side heats up and the other side cools. So one issue is that the heat from the hot side will seep into the cold side thus losing efficiency. To rectify that we added a heatsinkand a fan to the hot side so the heat dissapates faster. On the other side we had it hooked up to a small container of water in which we ran through a pump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/beer2/peltierconfig.jpg&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The system here shows the heatsink, fan and peltier and water unit.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the full setup that we have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/beer2/fullsetup.jpg&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Complete configuration&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We run water through a small tank that gets cooled by the peliter plate. Simple! Well it rarely is.  The water wasn&amp;rsquo;t cooling. With numerous factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our peltier plate wasnt heating at it maximum potential. The power supply we used is only rated for maximum of 3 amps. This only lowered our temperature on the cold side of the pletier plate to about 10°C&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/beer2/voltage.jpg&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Current limitations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our preliminary test we simply put the heatsink on top of the peltier plate and the plate to the water tank. This configuration does not transfer heat well at all due to the uneven surfaces.
Lastly, The water cooling tank was too small for a flowrate that was too fast. The water didn&amp;rsquo;t have time to actually get cold before moving out of the tank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all the goal of testing or sensors was done. We are going to need a new laod cell or figure out whats wrong with this one. The temperature sensors work well. We just need to figure out some more design parameters before we make the real thing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2016: A year in review</title>
      <link>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2017/01/31/awards/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2017/01/31/awards/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;reflections&#34;&gt;Reflections&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/awards/sf.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2016 has been a very exciting year for the Chem-E-Car team. We have presented our work in more than 7 conferences, with topics ranging from the clean energy industry (Generate 2016) to chemical engineering innovation (CHBE Engineering Research Day). From these events, we have won 5 different awards. Notably, we placed 1st among 41 teams from all over the world for our poster presentation at the American Institute of Chemical Engineers (AIChE) 2016 Student Conference in San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to our successes in these events, the team has also progressed and grown immensely. From a small group of 5 students just two years ago, the team has developed to a 40+ member organization. Aside from our Chem-E-Car activities, we have also started working on two more projects including a rechargeable microgrid system, and an integrated hardware/software beer brewing app for the AIChE National App Competition. To accommodate increasing student interests in our projects, we have streamlined our organizational structure and established a very dedicated and passionate junior Chem-E-Car team. We intend to send two cars to compete in the 2017 Pacific Northwest Regionals Chem-E-Car Competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our equipment has also been upgraded thanks to an extremely generous donation from our Exclusive Diamond Sponsor, the Daniel Family Foundation. We would also like to thank: Precision NanoSystems, BotFeeder, MG Chemicals, Digital Ocean, FortisBC, and CHBE for all of their support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2016-2017 period promises to be extremely exciting for Chem-E-Car as we have been invited to compete as the representatives of Canada at the
10th Annual World Chemical Engineering Congress to be held in Barcelona.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recent-awards&#34;&gt;Recent Awards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2017 CHBE Engineering Research Day - Best Presentation (Beer Brewing Automation Project)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 AIChE Nationals Chem-E-Car Poster Competition (San Francisco, 1st Place)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 UBC SPE Student Chapter LNG Case Competition (2nd Place)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 AIChE Pacific Northwest Regionals Chem-E-Car Poster Presentation (1st Place)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 AIChE Pacific Northwest Regionals Chem-E-Car Competition (2nd Place, Qualified for Nationals)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 CHBE Engineering Research Day - Best Presentation (Undergraduate Design Team Category)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2015 LNG in BC Conference - First Runner-up (Innovation Engineering Poster Presentation)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;events-and-outreach-programs&#34;&gt;Events and Outreach Programs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 Clean Energy in BC: Generate Conference - Poster Presentations on Zinc-Air Batteries and Biofuels (November 2016)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 IMechE President (Jon Hilton) Campus Tour and Luncheon Session - UBC Mech Department invitation (June 2016)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 IEEE PEDG Conference 2016 - Invitation for Student Team Exhibition on Renewable Energy (June 2016)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 Vancouver Mini Maker Faire at the PNE - Exhibitor (June 2016)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 UBC Golf Tournament Invitation Dinner - Sponsor Appreciation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 Sponsor Appreciation Night for Engineering Design Teams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 CHBE Research Day Poster Presentation and Podium Presentation for undergraduate design teams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 ACEC Transportation Conference Presentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 General Motors campus tour presentation - meet and greet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 Geering Up! Presentation - demos and hands-on activities for campers&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 CHBE Open House for prospective first year engineering students&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2015 EG-Fest at the Vancouver Public Library - Invited by APEGBC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2015 International BC in LNG Conference - Innovation Engineering Presentation&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2015 APSC Open House for prospective UBC Engineering students&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2015 UBC Imagine Day exhibition for first year students&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2015 UBC Jump Start - Engineering Design Team Introductions&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chem-E-Car Reaction Mechanism</title>
      <link>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2017/01/27/iodine-clock/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2017/01/27/iodine-clock/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Iodine Clock reaction is the official stopping mechanism for the 2016-2017 Junior Chem-E-Car design team. The reaction involves a color change with an Iodine indicator to signal the stopping mechanism, via a light dependent resistor. Through calibration, the reaction time can be determined by the ratio of Potassium Iodide and Sodium Thiosulfate. The correlation between time and ratio is linear; therefore, the Iodine Clock is a simple and effective stopping mechanism for the motor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-does-it-work&#34;&gt;How does it work?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two simultaneous chemical reactions shown below cause a color change from colorless to dark purple with a transient light blue intermediate stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-h-sub-2-sub-o-sub-2-sub-aq-2i-sup-sup-aq-2h-sup-sup-aq-i-sub-2-sub-2h-sub-2-sub-o-aq&#34;&gt;1. H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; (aq) + 2I&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt;(aq) + 2H&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;(aq)→ I&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; + 2H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O (aq)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-2s-sub-2-sub-o-sub-3-sub-sup-2-sup-aq-i-sub-2-sub-aq-s-sub-4-sub-o-sub-6-sub-sup-2-sup-aq-2i-sup-sup-aq&#34;&gt;2. 2S&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2−&lt;/sup&gt;(aq)+ I&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;(aq)→ S&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2−&lt;/sup&gt;(aq) + 2I&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt; (aq)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/iodine-clock/figure1.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1:&lt;/strong&gt; Color changes during the iodine clock reaction [Ref. 1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first reaction slowly oxidizes iodide ions (I-) into iodine (I2) which has the potential to
form a blue triiodide – starch complex. The second reaction rapidly reduces the product (I2)
from the first reaction back into its ionic form (I-). Due to the reaction rate difference, only
same amount of triiodide exists in the solution which maintains the colorless state of the
mixture. When thiosulfate ions (2S&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2−&lt;/sup&gt;) are exhausted, chemical equilibrium moves to the
accumulation and the solution turns from colorless into dark blue. In this calibration process, the concentration of thiosulfate ions acts as the limiting reagent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;general-procedure&#34;&gt;General Procedure:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the testing process, our team has to prepare multiple solutions with varying concentrations. We begin by preparing solution A and B (explained in detail below), mixing them, observing and recording the color change. After a large enough spread of data points are recorded, we can generate a calibration curve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-by-step-procedure&#34;&gt;Step-by-step Procedure:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preparation of solution A&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measure 6.0 g Na2S2O3 with an analytic balance and a weighing boat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dissolve 6.0 g Na2S2O3 in a 250ml volumetric flask. (Note: Dissolve Na2S2O3 within
the weighing boat first and then transfer the solution into the flask.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fill in the volumetric flask with DI water up to the graduation marking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measure 6.0g KI with an analytic balance and a weighing boat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dissolve 6.0g KI in a 250ml volumetric flask. (Note: Dissolve KI within the
weighing boat first and then transfer the solution into the flask.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fill in the volumetric flask with DI water up to the graduation marking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measure volume of both solutions needed, and mix in a 250 mL beaker.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preparation of solution B&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fill in the volumetric flask with distilled water up to the graduation marking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measure 40 ml 2M H2SO4 with a pipette into the 500ml volumetric flask.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measure 5 ml 30% H2O2 with a pipette into a 500ml volumetric flask.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measure 45ml prepared solution from the volumetric flask with a graduated cylinder as solution B.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transfer solution B from the graduated cylinder into a 50ml beaker as the testing container.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heat up 50 mL of DI water to approximately 45-50 degrees celsius. Measure and dissolve 2g of soluble starch in the water.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transfer 3 mL of the starch solution into the 50mL beaker with solution B.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mixing Solutions and Data Calibration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mix and adjust ratio of KI and Na2S2O3 in Solution A&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measure 10 mL of Solution A in syringe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transfer 40 mL of Solution B to beaker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inject Solution A into Solution B to mix and start timing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stop time once color change initiates and record&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat steps 1-5 for different ratios of KI and Na2S2O3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plot calibration to find relationship between time and ratio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/iodine-clock/figure2.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2:&lt;/strong&gt; Calibration curve plotting reaction time vs volumetric ratio of solution A to solution B&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Iodine clock reaction displays a linear relationship between reaction time and the ratio between the volumes of Potassium Iodide and Sodium Thiosulfate added. As a result, we can manipulate the volume of our Potassium Iodide solution added to interpolate for a specific stopping time. Our goal is to maintain an error of less than 2% for our calibration curve. The Iodine Clock reaction is a reliable and simple method for timing the motor of the car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://img.wonderhowto.com/img/18/99/63483049134215/0/classic-chemistry-colorize-colorless-liquids-with-black-magic-aka-iodine-clock-reaction.1280x600.jpg&#34;&gt;Classic chemistry colorize colorless liquids with black magic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biofuels Project</title>
      <link>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2017/01/19/biofuels/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2017/01/19/biofuels/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;prologue&#34;&gt;Prologue&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Casually during our regular weekday meeting, Siang and Thanos discussed the idea of having two teams from Chem E Car present posters at the annual Generate conference hosted by Clean Energy BC. We decided to be that second team. With less than a month away, we had to choose a topic, become experts in that topic and design a poster in hopes of winning the competition and $500 prize money. What started off as a one-time project has turned into a team interest and has some of our members looking to pursue it further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As one of the fastest growing plants, algae uses sunlight more effectively than any other plant resulting in it having up to 2x higher energy production compared to other crops. With a composition of 50% oil by dry weight, algae is the ideal crop to use for biofuel. After significant technological advancements in growing algae, oil extraction, and biofuel conversion, the overall cost can potentially be reduced to USD $1.94 per gallon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/biofuels/biofuels.png&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/biofuels/biofuels.pdf&#34;&gt;Our beautiful biofuels poster&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;growth-of-algae&#34;&gt;Growth of Algae&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When compared to other oil producing crops, algae can produce up to 10 times more oil per hectare of land. Algae can also grow in a wide variety of environments, including saltwater, freshwater, glaciers, and even wastewater. Since algae grows in water, algae can be grown on non arable land. Algae uses sunlight and CO2 to grow, which means that CO2 emissions from power plants and factories that are normally sequestered into the ground can be redirected to grow algae, and make the biofuel a carbon sink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;production-methods&#34;&gt;Production methods&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two main methods of growing algae, open systems and closed systems. Open systems have low control over the process, low productivity, low operation costs, and high contamination risk when compared to closed systems. This contrast causes a large argument over which method is superior. At the moment, open systems are more favourable since they are much cheaper. We believe that when the technology improves, closed systems will be the future of algae farming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;future-of-algae&#34;&gt;Future of Algae&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a lack of affordable technology, algae biofuels are currently a very expensive alternative to traditional fossil fuels. Despite this, from a research perspective, algae biofuels have the highest potential to replace these traditional fossil fuels. A lot of work needs to be done before algae becomes the leader of energy production for the transportation industry. The sheer magnitude of algae that can be produced from a small plot of non-arable land makes it the only viable option that can replace Big Oil and save our world from climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;poster&#34;&gt;Poster&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out our poster for more information: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/biofuels/biofuels.pdf&#34;&gt;Poster Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beer Homebrew Project</title>
      <link>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2017/01/12/beer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2017/01/12/beer/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the Student AIChE/CACHE National Mobile Device APP Competition around the corner, our team has been working hard in exploring different ideas to showcase our creativity in a practical design. As part of our lab course field trips, many of us have visited local breweries to gain a general overview of how the general brewing process works. Keeping this in mind, we decided to try something that none of us have done before: creating an app to automate the brewing of craft beer. To create this app, we first had to be confident in carrying out the brewing process itself. Thus, we are proud to present the CHBE Brewing team, a sub-division of the Chem-E-Car team!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/beer/logo.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Logo design courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amandapenuta.com/&#34;&gt;Amanda Penuta&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;literature-review&#34;&gt;Literature Review&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We began with browsing the web on what kind of equipment would be required to begin brewing. Without any prior experience in brewing, it was difficult to know whether we really &lt;strong&gt;needed&lt;/strong&gt; that $300 &amp;ldquo;All-in-One Reactor&amp;rdquo;. Instead, we chose to drop by some local homebrewing businesses to learn more about the process. We ended up going to Centennial Homebrewing Supplies and speaking with the owner, Brian Janzen. Brian was extremely informative, guiding us through the steps of homebrewing; from choosing the right equipment for beginner brewing, to bottling the brew at the very end. His tutorial can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mxdreV_tN1Y/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-brewing-process&#34;&gt;The Brewing Process&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/beer/flowchart.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Overview of the extract brewing process that we followed.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sanitizing&#34;&gt;Sanitizing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed with this new knowledge, we purchased the equipment and got to work. We began with sanitizing all the equipment with Sani-brew (1 tbsp. powder/L of water) cleaning solution. This is to ensure that chance of bacterial growth or contamination is minimized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mashing&#34;&gt;Mashing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step is to &amp;ldquo;mash the grains&amp;rdquo;. Contrary to what we initially thought, it had nothing to do with physically mashing the grains. This step involved adding 1L of water for each lb of grain that we had (2.5L of water in our case) to a pot and bringing the temperature up to ~145 to 155°F (~63 to 68°C). This mixture was then allowed to steep for about 60 minutes. Due to the uneven heating from the stove we were using, the grains ended up being slightly burnt&amp;hellip; but that just adds more flavor to the brew, right? (To be confirmed)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sparging&#34;&gt;Sparging&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the grains were steeping, another pot of water was heated up to about 175°F (~79°C). This pot of water was used in the sparging (rinsing) step. This was done by pouring the steeped grains mixture into a colander, and the additional water through the grains into another pot. The liquid that drains through is the base of our wort, while the spent grains were disposed of. The liquid malt extract was added to the wort base and stirred well until the mixture was uniform. This was done before the stove was turned on to prevent the mixture from burning and sticking to the bottom of the pot. The mixture was then brought to a boil. During this boiling time, the primary fermenter was sanitized using the Sani-brew cleaning solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;boiling&#34;&gt;Boiling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the wort was boiling, we set a timer for 60 minutes of boiling. Throughout this timeframe, hops were added at different times. For example, the Pacific ESB we were making required the 3 bags of hops to be added in at 0 minutes (beginning of boil), 45 minutes, and 55 minutes of boiling time. Once the boiling time was complete, the wort was then plunged into an ice bath to cool it down. As Vancouver has been experiencing heavy snowfall (by our standards), our ice bath consisted of snow and ice taken from right outside our doorstep. Once the wort reached a temperature of around ~69 to 73°F (~20.5 to 23°C), it was poured into the primary fermenter. The primary fermenter was topped off with water so the total volume of the brew was about 23L, with the temperature being around 21°C for optimal yeast pitching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;fermenting&#34;&gt;Fermenting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the yeast was added to the wort, a test was conducted using a hydrometer. This showed the starting gravity of the wort, with the potential final alcohol content (around 6.5% for our brew). The yeast was added to the wort and the primary fermenter was sealed with an airlock (this allows carbon dioxide to escape during fermentation, but nothing to go into the brew). The primary fermenter was then left to sit for about a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conditioning&#34;&gt;Conditioning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a week of fermentation, the brew was transported into the carboy for conditioning and additional fermentation. The brew was siphoned out using a tube with a filter attached to the end to prevent larger solids from going through. Once all the brew was transported to the carboy, it was sealed with another airlock and left to sit for another week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a total of two weeks of fermentation, the brew was about ready to bottle. Another test was done with the hydrometer (pictured below) to see if the fermentation was near completion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/beer/hydrometer.jpg&#34; height=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;It was recommended that the reading on the hydrometer to be around 1008 to 1010, which indicates that fermentation was near completion. Our reading was roughly 1014, so pretty close.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bottling-and-carbonation&#34;&gt;Bottling and Carbonation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, the brew was basically flat (not a lot of carbonation). The next step involved adding &lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; cup of dextrose (priming sugar) into the brew before bottling. Since the bottles are left capped for two more weeks, the priming sugar causes carbonation to occur. The brew was siphoned into two types of bottles that we purchased: 1L EZ-cap bottles and 330mL bottles with crown caps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/beer/capper.jpg&#34; height=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Capping is hard work. (No, it&amp;rsquo;s not)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/beer/bottles.jpg&#34; height=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Bottled and ready to drink! (In two weeks)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we just need to wait about one more week from this time of posting for the carbonation to finalize. Hopefully we will have great tasting beer to drink!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solder Fan System</title>
      <link>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2017/01/01/solder-fan-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2017/01/01/solder-fan-system/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing around with old computer power supplies. Naturally, that led me to other components of the computer, namely, the cooling fan. These fans are driven by a brushless DC motor system. This is to achieve a reduced sound and higher efficiency compared to a brushed DC motor system such as those you would see (or hear) in printers, air conditioners and RC cars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computer fans can range from very simple to kind-of-simple with 2, 3, and 4 wires coming out of it. The 2 wire configuration is the simplest and this is just power and ground. A third wire is introduced to be able to monitor the speed of the fan. This is done most commonly by using a hall sensor to measure the rotations of the rotors around the commutator. The 4th wire adds PWM control to the fan so that consumers can control the speed of the fan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/solder-fan/2wirefan.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;A two wire fan circuit. Check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://pcbheaven.com/wikipages/How_PC_Fans_Work/&#34;&gt;PCB Heaven&lt;/a&gt; for more info&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How useful are these fans? Under normal operating temperatures, the pi typically reaches ~68 C, and ~80 C when performing calculations or running a video. With the fan, the temperature is quickly lowered to ~37 C. Another use for these fans is for soldering. They create a vaccuum to garner the toxic fumes from the solder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soldering fumes are bad for you! They are a mix of lead, and rosin evaporated into a gas. Always have good ventilation when you solder. I use my PC fans to create a solder fume extractor that I would otherwise, have to buy commercially &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.digikey.ca/product-detail/en/apex-tool-group/WSA350/WSA350-ND/1130559&#34;&gt;like this&lt;/a&gt;. I created a tiny switch board for my fans and I had them running! This was a good start but it didnt fully solve the problem as the fumes were merely being diluted. To rectify this I bought some carbon filters and attached them onto my fans. The trade-off is that this lowers the volume of air displaced by the fan but fumes actually become trapped by the carbon filter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The circuit I used was a simple switch inline to a computer power supply to power the fans. I am a large fan (no pun intended) of modularity, the ability to switch and recombine components. Sometimes, I need the power supply for a different task, or I need the fan to be cooling rather than extracting particulates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My circuit was simple enough that I didnt need a breadboard. I also wanted my circuit to be more permanent and didn&amp;rsquo;t want to spend time or money making a PCB, so I went with a perf board. Perfboards come in many varieties with copper strips exactly like a breadboard or long strips down the board but they are known traditionally as boards with arrays of little holes punched into them and copper vias surrounding them to create a contact for soldering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perfboards are a step behind making an actual PCB that you would see inside any electronic component but I believe that they are more difficult to make. With CAD software out there such as EAGLECAD or Fritzing, making a PCB is very visual. The graphical interfaces allow you to easily create a route and undo it with a simple click of a button. With a perfboard it is more difficult as there isn&amp;rsquo;t this interface. Planning it becomes a lot more tedious with pencil and paper and having to make iterations&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/solder-fan/circuit.jpg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my perfboard I used two rows of header pins to allow multiple fan systems as well as the connection to the power supply. A set-screw hub enable the switch to be inserted and removed at a moments notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I just need to wait for my fans to come in from the internet (that was a pun)!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How To Create Dynamic Org Charts With Google Sheets and Javascript</title>
      <link>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2016/12/24/orgcharts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2016/12/24/orgcharts/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/chart/interactive/docs/&#34;&gt;Google Chart&lt;/a&gt; library provides a convenient way of visualizing datasets using Javascript and embedding them in websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/team/&#34;&gt;team page&lt;/a&gt;, we wanted to embed a dynamic orgchart that would be updated automatically using values stored in a Google Docs &amp;lsquo;database&amp;rsquo;. Finding online tutorials for this was a bit challenging, so here&amp;rsquo;s our implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If all goes well, you should get something like this, with the names, roles and relationships defined in a Google Sheet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/orgcharts/1.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-it-works&#34;&gt;How it works&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will be using the &lt;code&gt;orgchart&lt;/code&gt; package in Google Charts. Our implementation will be somewhat similar to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/chart/interactive/docs/gallery/orgchart&#34;&gt;example&lt;/a&gt; in the Google Charts documentation, but instead of hardcoding the values in JavaScript, we will grab them dynamically from a Google Sheet data source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;set-up-your-google-sheet&#34;&gt;Set up your Google Sheet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, create a new Google Sheet with a title of your choice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the first row, fill in the first 3 columns, A to C, with &amp;lsquo;Role&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Reports To&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;Name&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add in your team&amp;rsquo;s roles, names and organizational relationships in the subsequent rows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Role&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first column contains the role of the team member (i.e. Captain, Treasurer, Secretary). This is the green colored text in the screenshot above. The &lt;strong&gt;roles must be unique&lt;/strong&gt; or the orgchart won&amp;rsquo;t work properly. If you have multiple people with the same roles, add numbers or Roman numerals at the end (i.e. Webmaster I, Webmaster II).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reports To&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This column defines the relationships in the orgchart. Fill it up with the &lt;strong&gt;role&lt;/strong&gt; that this position reports to. A blank entry will place the box at the very top of the org chart. (i.e. the &lt;strong&gt;Reports To&lt;/strong&gt; entry for Captain will be blank).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-explanatory, this column contains the names of the team members. This is the black colored text in the screenshot above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you&amp;rsquo;re done, your Google Sheet should look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/orgcharts/2.png&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;grab-your-google-sheet-data-in-json-format&#34;&gt;Grab your Google Sheet data in JSON format&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once that&amp;rsquo;s done, click the big blue share button on the top right corner of the screen and change the sharing settings to &amp;lsquo;Anyone with the link &lt;strong&gt;Can View&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rsquo;. Copy the URL for your Google Sheet from your browser, it should look something like this:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1qImsDykMfz-obbMsOQo6f_IW_xmNdtScByEhcnfU3S8/edit#gid=0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To get the data as a JSON file, modify the &lt;code&gt;edit#gid=0&lt;/code&gt; part to &lt;code&gt;gviz/tq&lt;/code&gt;, as below:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1qImsDykMfz-obbMsOQo6f_IW_xmNdtScByEhcnfU3S8/gviz/tq&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you navigate to that link in your browser, you should get a &lt;code&gt;json.txt&lt;/code&gt; file. You will need this link for the next step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;javascript-implementation&#34;&gt;Javascript Implementation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the Google Sheet &amp;lsquo;database&amp;rsquo; has been set up, create a new &lt;code&gt;orgchart.html&lt;/code&gt; (or any other name) file and paste in the following code. We will be using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/chart/interactive/docs/reference#queryobjects&#34;&gt;Google Visualization API Query Language&lt;/a&gt; to help us grab data from our Google Sheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember to replace &lt;code&gt;var dataSourceUrl&lt;/code&gt; with your own Google Sheet URL. Open the file in your browser, and you should see your orgchart!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-html&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;div id=&amp;quot;orgchart_admin&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;script src=&amp;quot;https://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/1.9.1/jquery.min.js&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;script type=&amp;quot;text/javascript&amp;quot; src=&amp;quot;https://www.gstatic.com/charts/loader.js&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;script type=&amp;quot;text/javascript&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    google.charts.load(&#39;current&#39;, {&#39;packages&#39; : [&#39;orgchart&#39;, &#39;table&#39;]});
    google.charts.setOnLoadCallback(function() { initialize(&#39;&#39;) });

    function initialize() {
      document.getElementById(&#39;orgchart_admin&#39;).innerHTML = &amp;quot;&amp;lt;i class=&#39;fa fa-spinner fa-spin fa-3x fa-fw&#39;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;&amp;quot;;
      
      var dataSourceUrl = &#39;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1qImsDykMfz-obbMsOQo6f_IW_xmNdtScByEhcnfU3S8/gviz/tq?&#39;;

      // Tells it that the first row contains headers: &#39;Role&#39;, &#39;Reports To&#39;, &#39;Name&#39;
      var query = new google.visualization.Query(dataSourceUrl + &#39;&amp;amp;headers=1&#39;);

      // Send the query with a callback function.
      query.send(handleQueryResponse);
    }

    function handleQueryResponse(response) {
      // Called when the query response is returned.
      if (response.isError()) {
        alert(&#39;Error in query: &#39; + response.getMessage() + &#39; &#39; + response.getDetailedMessage());
        return;
      }

      var raw_data = response.getDataTable();
      var data = new google.visualization.DataTable();

      data.addColumn(&#39;string&#39;, &#39;Entity&#39;);
      data.addColumn(&#39;string&#39;, &#39;ParentEntity&#39;);
      data.addColumn(&#39;string&#39;, &#39;ToolTip&#39;);

      // Loops through all rows and populates a new DataTable with formatted values for the orgchart
      var num_rows = raw_data.getNumberOfRows();
      for (var i = 0; i &amp;lt; num_rows; i++) {
        var role = raw_data.getValue(i, 0);
        var reportsTo = raw_data.getValue(i,1);
        var name = raw_data.getValue(i,2) != null ? raw_data.getValue(i,2) : &#39;&#39;;

        data.addRows([[
          { v: role,
            f: name + &amp;quot;&amp;lt;div class=&#39;role&#39;&amp;gt;&amp;quot; + role + &amp;quot;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&amp;quot;
          }, 
          reportsTo, 
          name]]);
      }

      // Loops through all rows and populates a new DataTable with formatted values for the orgchart
      var container = document.getElementById(&#39;orgchart_admin&#39;);
      var chart = new google.visualization.OrgChart(container);
      chart.draw(data, {allowHtml:true, &#39;size&#39;: &#39;large&#39;});
    }      
  &amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;breaking-down-the-script&#34;&gt;Breaking down the script&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;code&gt;initialize()&lt;/code&gt; function, we used the &lt;code&gt;Query&lt;/code&gt; class to grab data from our Google Sheet. This is very similar to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/chart/interactive/docs/spreadsheets&#34;&gt;example&lt;/a&gt; in the documentation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;code&gt;handleQueryResponse()&lt;/code&gt; callback function, if the query is successful, we can get the data as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/chart/interactive/docs/datatables_dataviews&#34;&gt;DataTable&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;code&gt;raw_data = response.getDataTable()&lt;/code&gt;. A DataTable is essentially an array of columns and rows used by Google Charts to represent chart data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We then looped through our &lt;code&gt;raw_data&lt;/code&gt; and populated a new DataTable, &lt;code&gt;var data = new google.visualization.DataTable()&lt;/code&gt;. We did this row by row with the &lt;code&gt;addRows()&lt;/code&gt; function. We did this because the &lt;code&gt;orgchart&lt;/code&gt; package takes in 3 columns, according to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/chart/interactive/docs/gallery/orgchart&#34;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt; and we want to add formatted values to the first column:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Column&lt;/strong&gt;
The first column is the node ID (each node is a box in the org chart) and as previously mentioned, it should be unique. We can either show the node ID in the box, or use a prettier formatted value, &lt;code&gt;f&lt;/code&gt; to show in the box, but the unformatted value, &lt;code&gt;v&lt;/code&gt; is still used as the ID. Having formatted values allows us to display the name and role (or optionally, even more data like pictures) in different colors in the same box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our orgchart, we want to display both the name and the role, with the role in a different color. So in the code above, we defined the formatted value as follows, with &lt;code&gt;div&lt;/code&gt; tags around &lt;code&gt;role&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;f: name + &amp;quot;&amp;lt;div class=&#39;role&#39;&amp;gt;&amp;quot; + role + &amp;quot;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Second Column&lt;/strong&gt;
The second column defines the parent node of the current box (i.e. the relationship data) using the unformatted value, &lt;code&gt;v&lt;/code&gt; of the parent node. If this is left blank, the node will be defined as a root node.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Third Column&lt;/strong&gt;
The third and optional column defines the tooltip text, the text that pops up when you hover your mouse over the box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, in the last part of the script, we made a call to &lt;code&gt;new google.visualization.OrgChart()&lt;/code&gt; to display our chart in the web page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;var container = document.getElementById(&#39;orgchart_admin&#39;);
var chart = new google.visualization.OrgChart(container);
chart.draw(data, {allowHtml:true, &#39;size&#39;: &#39;large&#39;});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;styling-the-org-chart&#34;&gt;Styling the org chart&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, we&amp;rsquo;ve managed to display our org chart, but we haven&amp;rsquo;t added the formatting yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/orgcharts/3.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To change the text color for the roles in the box, we need to add some CSS. Let&amp;rsquo;s modify the head section in the code above:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-html&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;style&amp;gt;
  .role{
      font-size: small;
      color: #1aa;
  }   
  &amp;lt;/style&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should now see the font size and colors updated for the roles if you refresh your page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/orgcharts/4.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it! Using CSS, you can also style the names by wrapping them with div tags. You can also play around with the box colors, font size and anything else in the org chart. Refer to the Google Charts &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/chart/interactive/docs/gallery/orgchart&#34;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt; for further information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;f: &amp;quot;&amp;lt;div class=&#39;name&#39;&amp;gt;&amp;quot; + name + &amp;quot;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&amp;quot; + &amp;quot;&amp;lt;div class=&#39;role&#39;&amp;gt;&amp;quot; + role + &amp;quot;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Importance of Trial and Error</title>
      <link>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2016/11/24/trial-and-error/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.ubcchemecar.com/blog/2016/11/24/trial-and-error/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome everyone to the first of (hopefully) many blog posts for the UBC Chem-E-Car Team. The purpose of these posts is to give you, the reader insight into how our organization is run. Through this we hope to generate interest in our organization and to help get other students involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The topic of our first post is on the importance of trial and error. Most people will look at a finished product and comment on how sleek or amazing it is; while conveniently ignoring that it took years of tinkering and modifications for that item to even function properly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First let’s take a look at the first electronic circuit that I ever made for Chem-E-Car:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/trial-and-error/first.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;First&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entire device is a mess! There are wires everywhere, tons of unused board real estate, and parts that have to be tied together to fit on the board. Likewise, unsecured parts have a very unreliable connection and break off easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the summer I made a new model with the focus of eliminating loose wires and better utilizing space, this is the result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/trial-and-error/second.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Second&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This model utilizes a lot less space, is easy to stack, and most of the components are stabilized on the board itself. However, during assembly I needed a lot of extra parts since directly soldering them often destroyed the part if not done properly. Another issue is that the model needed 4 stacks (making it really tall), and the lights and switches were not necessary. Now let’s look at the second iteration:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/trial-and-error/third.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Third&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The board is even MORE compact, features detachable modules for easy replacement, and utilizes an SD card and opto-gate for recording data. However, the connectors were unreliable, the copper on the board was unprotected and prone to damage which destroyed the circuit at times, and data could not be read in real time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To fix these issues I developed a 4th and final board:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/trial-and-error/fourth.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Fourth&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This system uses reliable connectors that can only be inserted in one direction, is completely modular (easy to replace destroyed parts), has a silkscreen layer that protects the circuit, only uses one layer, and utilizes a bluetooth system for real time data collection on a mobile phone!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an image of all the circuits for an overall comparison:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/trial-and-error/comparison.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Comparison&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;reflections&#34;&gt;Reflections&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These circuits are 1.5 years of continuous design and iteration, with each model having its flaws analyzed and corrected. They were made by an entry level chemical engineering student with NO prior experience or knowledge of electronics. The moral of the story? Good design is all about making something, figuring out what works and doesn’t work then rebuilding it until it sort of works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.ubcchemecar.com/img/blog/trial-and-error/quote.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Quote&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to any beginner in terms of design, don’t despair! Rather look at what you can learn from your prototype and how it can be improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that sense it is important to seek the feedback of experienced individuals. Their experience (in how NOT to do things wrong by doing it wrong) is invaluable for any would-be inventor. Look at how others have done things and learn accordingly from it. Finally remember, every master in a subject started from knowing nothing; the difference between them and the amateurs is that they never stopped trying to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>